<!-- ------------------------------------------------------------------- -->
<!--                                                                     -->
<!--  gslp.xml                Utils documentation                        -->
<!--                                                                     -->
<!--  Copyright (C) 2026, The GAP Group                                  -->
<!--                                                                     -->
<!-- ------------------------------------------------------------------- -->

<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<Chapter Label="chap-gslp">
<Heading>Generalized Straight Line Programs</Heading>

The functions described in this chapter have been written by Thomas Breuer,
they are available since <Package>Utils</Package> 0.94.
<P/>
<E>Generalized straight line programs</E> (in the following abbreviated
as <E>gslps</E>) are a generalization of the straight line programs
that are described in the &GAP; library,
see <Ref Sect="Straight Line Programs" BookName="ref"/>.
Like the latter objects, gslps describe an efficient way for evaluating
an abstract word at concrete generators.
The difference is that gslps can be built
from existing (generalized) straight line programs,
whereas a straight line program is given by an explicit list of
instructions (see <Ref Func="LinesOfStraightLineProgram" BookName="ref"/>).
So the advantages of using a gslp instead of constructing an equivalent
straight line program (see <Ref Func="EquivalentStraightLineProgram"/>)
are that
<P/>
<List>
<Item>
    available objects (the building blocks of the gslp) are reused,
</Item>
<Item>
    the internal structure of the gslp is retained
    (one can access the building blocks if one wants), and
</Item>
<Item>
    in the evaluation of a gslp, the intermediate results that arise in
    a building block of the gslp can be garbage collected
    as soon as the evaluation of this building block has finished.
</Item>
</List>
<P/>
A gslp in &GAP; is represented by an object in the category
<Ref Filt="IsGeneralizedStraightLineProgram"/>.
This object has exactly one of the following forms.
<P/>
<List>
<Item>
    It is a straight line program, that is, it lies in the
    category <Ref Filt="IsStraightLineProgram" BookName="ref"/>,
    and evaluation at some group elements is defined by
    <Ref Oper="ResultOfStraightLineProgram" BookName="ref"/>.
</Item>
<Item>
    It is of <Q>union</Q> kind, that is, the defining data are
    a nonempty list <M>l</M> of gslps,
    and evaluation at some group elements means to evaluate the
    gslps in <M>l</M> at these group elements,
    and to return the concatenation of the results.
</Item>
<Item>
    It is of <Q>compose</Q> kind, that is, the defining data are
    a nonempty list <M>l</M> of gslps,
    and evaluation at some group elements means
    to evaluate <M>l[1]</M> at these elements,
    then to evaluate <M>l[2]</M> at the result of the first
    evaluation,
    and so on, and to return the last result.
</Item>
</List>
<P/>
Here are two typical situations where gslps arise.
In both cases, suppose that a list <M>l</M> of standard generators
for a group <M>G</M> is given.
<P/>
<Enum>
<Item>
    Suppose that we know a straight line program for computing generators
    <M>l'</M> of a maximal subgroup <M>M</M> of <M>G</M> from <M>l</M>.
    For example, these data may be taken from the
    <Package>ATLAS</Package> of Group Representations <Cite Key="AGRv3"/>.
    If <M>M</M> is also a group for which the
    <Package>ATLAS</Package> of Group Representations contains generators
    and straight line programs,
    we may be interested in computing standard generators <M>l''</M>
    for <M>M</M> from <M>l'</M>.
    <P/>
    For that, a second straight line program may be needed,
    and it makes sense to encode the computation of <M>l''</M> from
    <M>l</M> via a gslp of <Q>compose</Q> kind.
</Item>
<Item>
    Suppose that we are in fact interested in a downward extension
    <M>H</M> of <M>G</M>, and that <M>\pi</M> is the natural epimorphism
    from <M>H</M> to <M>G</M>, which maps a list <M>L</M>, say,
    of standard generators of <M>H</M> to <M>l</M>.
    Then the above gslp for <M>G</M> can be applied to <M>L</M>,
    but the result <M>L'</M> may generate a proper subgroup of
    <M>\pi^{-1}(M)</M> because some part of the kernel of <M>\pi</M> is
    missing.
    <P/>
    A list <M>K</M> of generators of the kernel of <M>\pi</M> can be
    described by a straight line program that takes <M>L</M> as its
    input, and it makes sense to encode the computation of the
    concatenation of <M>L'</M> and <M>K</M> from <M>L</M> via a gslp of
    <Q>union</Q> kind.
</Item>
</Enum>
<P/>

Gslps can be constructed using <Ref Func="GeneralizedStraightLineProgram"
Label="for kind and list"/>.
<P/>
Defining attributes for gslps are
<Ref Attr="NrInputsOfGeneralizedStraightLineProgram"/>
and <Ref Attr="DataOfGeneralizedStraightLineProgram"/>.
The probably most interesting operation for gslps is
<Ref Oper="ResultOfGeneralizedStraightLineProgram"/>.
<P/>
Currently we do not intend to provide methods applicable to
generalized straight line programs for all operations that are defined for
straight line programs.
For example,
there is no <Ref Func="IntermediateResultOfSLP" BookName="ref"/> method
for generalized straight line programs.
<P/>
Special methods applicable to gslps are installed for the operations
<Ref Meth="IsInternallyConsistent" Label="for gen. straight line program"/>,
<Ref Oper="ViewString" BookName="ref"/>,
and <Ref Oper="String" BookName="ref"/>.


<Section Label="sec-gslp">
<Heading>Functions for Generalized Straight Line Programs</Heading>

<#Include Label="IsGeneralizedStraightLineProgram">
<#Include Label="GeneralizedStraightLineProgram">
<#Include Label="DataOfGeneralizedStraightLineProgram">
<#Include Label="NrInputsOfGeneralizedStraightLineProgram">
<#Include Label="NrOutputsOfGeneralizedStraightLineProgram">
<#Include Label="ResultOfGeneralizedStraightLineProgram">
<#Include Label="EquivalentStraightLineProgram">
<#Include Label="IsInternallyConsistent_gslp">

</Section>

</Chapter>
