<!-- ------------------------------------------------------------------- -->
<!--                                                                     -->
<!--  intro.xml            Utils documentation            Chris Wensley  -->
<!--                                                                     -->
<!--  Copyright (C) 2015-2018, The GAP Group                             --> 
<!--                                                                     -->
<!-- ------------------------------------------------------------------- -->

<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> 

<Chapter Label="chap-intro">

<Heading>Introduction</Heading>

The &Utils; package provides a space for utility functions from a variety 
of &GAP; packages to be collected together into a single package. 
In this way it is hoped that they will become more visible 
to other package authors. 
This package was first distributed as part of the &GAP; 4.8.2 distribution. 
<P/> 

The package is loaded with the command
<Example>
<![CDATA[
gap> LoadPackage( "utils" ); 
]]>
</Example>
<P/>
Functions have been transferred from the following packages: 
<List>
<Item>
Conversion of a &GAP; group to a &Magma; output string, taken from various 
sources including <File>other.gi</File> in the main library. 
</Item>
</List>
<P/>
Transfer is complete (for now) for functions from the following packages:
<List>
<Item>
&AutoDoc; <Cite Key="AutoDoc" /> (with function names changed);
</Item>
<Item>
&ResClasses; <Cite Key="ResClasses" />;
</Item>
<Item>
&RCWA; <Cite Key="RCWA" />;
</Item>
<Item>
&XMod; <Cite Key="XMod" />.
</Item>
</List>
<P/>

The package may be obtained either as a compressed <Code>.tar</Code> file 
or as a <Code>.zip</Code> file, <File>utils-version_number.tar.gz</File>,
by ftp from one of the following sites: 
<List>
<Item>
the &Utils; GitHub release site: 
<URL>https://gap-packages.github.io/utils/</URL>. 
</Item>
<Item>
any &GAP; archive, e.g. 
<URL>https://www.gap-system.org/Packages/packages.html</URL>; 
</Item>
</List> 
<Index>GitHub repository</Index> 
The package also has a GitHub repository at: 
<URL>https://github.com/gap-packages/utils</URL>. 
<P/> 


Once the package is loaded, the manual <Code>doc/manual.pdf</Code> 
can be found in the documentation folder. 
The <Code>html</Code> versions, with or without &MathJax;, 
may be rebuilt as follows: 
<P/>
<Example>
<![CDATA[
gap> ReadPackage( "utils", "makedoc.g" ); 
]]>
</Example>
<P/>
It is possible to check that the package has been installed correctly
by running the test files (which terminates the &GAP; session): 
<P/>
<Example>
<![CDATA[
gap> ReadPackage( "utils", "tst/testall.g" );
Architecture: . . . . . 
testing: . . . . . 
. . . 
#I  No errors detected while testing
]]>
</Example>
<P/>

Note that functions listed in this manual that are currently 
in the process of being transferred 
are only read from the source package &Home; (say), 
and so can only be used if &Home; has already been loaded. 



<Section Label="sect-author-info"> 
<Heading>Information for package authors</Heading> 

A function (or collection of functions) is suitable for transfer 
from a package &Home; to &Utils; 
if the following conditions are satisfied. 
<List>
<Item>
The function is sufficiently non-specialised so that it might be of use 
to other authors.
</Item>
<Item>
The function does not depend on the remaining functions in &Home; 
</Item>
<Item>
The function does not do what can already be done with a &GAP; library function. 
</Item>
<Item>
Documentation of the function and test examples are available. 
</Item>
<Item>
When there is more than one active author of &Home;, they should all be aware 
(and content) that the transfer is taking place. 
</Item>
</List> 
<P/>

Authors of packages may be reluctant to let go of their utility functions. 
The following principles may help to reassure them. 
(Suggestions for more items here are welcome.) 

<List>
<Item> 
A function that has been transferred to &Utils; will not be changed 
without the approval of the original author. 
</Item>
<Item>
The current package maintainer has every intention of continuing 
to maintain &Utils;. 
In the event that this proves impossible, the &GAP; development team 
will surely find someone to take over. 
</Item>
<Item>
Function names will not be changed unless specifically requested by 
&Home;'s author(s) or unless they have the form 
<C>HOME_FunctionName</C>. 
</Item>
<Item>
In order to speed up the transfer process, only functions from one package
will be in transition at any given time.  
Hopefully a week or two will suffice for most packages. 
</Item>
<Item>
Any package author who transfers a function to &Utils; will become 
an author of &Utils;. 
(In truth, &Utils; does not have <E>authors</E>, 
just a large number of <E>contributors</E>.) 
</Item>
</List>
<P/>
The process for transferring utility functions from &Home; to &Utils; 
is described in Chapter <Ref Chap="chap-transfer" />.

</Section> 

</Chapter>
