<!-- ------------------------------------------------------------------- -->
<!--                                                                     -->
<!--  transfer.xml           Utils documentation          Chris Wensley  -->
<!--                                                                     -->
<!--  Copyright (C) 2015-2017, The GAP Group                             --> 
<!--                                                                     -->
<!-- ------------------------------------------------------------------- -->

<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> 

<Chapter Label="chap-transfer">

<Heading>The transfer procedure</Heading>

We consider here the process for transferring utility functions 
from a package &Home; to &Utils; which has to avoid the potential problem 
of duplicate declarations of a function causing loading problems in &GAP;. 
<P/>
If the functions in &Home; all have names of the form 
<C>HOME_FunctionName</C> then, in &Utils;, these functions 
are likely to be renamed as <C>FunctionName</C> or something similar. 
In this case the problem of duplicate declarations does not arise. 
This is what has happened with transfers from the <Package>AutoDoc</Package> 
package. 
<P/>
The case where the function names are unchanged is more complicated. 
Initially we tried out a process which allowed repeated declarations and 
installations of the functions being transferred. 
This involved additions to the main library files <File>global.g</File> 
and <File>oper.g</File>. 
Since there were misgivings about interfering in this way 
with basic operations such as <C>BIND_GLOBAL</C>, 
a simpler (but slightly less convenient) process has been adopted. 
<P/> 
Using this alternative procedure, the following steps will be followed 
when making transfers from &Home; to &Utils;. 

<Enum>
<Item>
(&Home;:)
Offer functions for inclusion. 
This may be simply done by emailing a list of functions. 
More usefully, email the declaration, implementation, test and 
documentation files, e.g.: <File>home.gd</File>, 
<File>home.gi</File>, <File>home.tst</File> and <File>home.xml</File>. 
(All active authors should be involved.) 
</Item>
<Item>
(&Home;:)
Declare that <B>m.n</B> is the last version of &Home; 
to contain these functions, so that <B>m.n+1</B> (or similar) 
will be the first version of &Home; to have all these functions 
removed, and to specify &Utils; as a required package. 
</Item>
<Item>
(&Utils;:)
Add strings <A>"home"</A> and <A>"m.n"</A> to the list 
<C>UtilsPackageVersions</C> in the file <File>utils/lib/start.gd</File>. 
<Example>
<![CDATA[
UtilsPackageVersions := 
  [ "autodoc",     "2016.01.31", 
    "resclasses",  "4.2.5", 
    "home",        "m.n",
    ...,           ... 
  ];
]]>
</Example>
While the transfers are being made, it is essential that any new versions 
of &Home; should be tested with the latest version of &Utils; 
before they are released, so as to avoid loading failures.  
</Item>
<Item>
(&Utils;:)
Include the function declaration and implementation sections 
in suitable files, enclosed within a conditional clause of the form: 
<Example>
<![CDATA[
if OKtoReadFromUtils( "Home" ) then
. . . . . . 
 <the code> 
. . . . . . 
fi;
]]>
</Example> 
<Index>OKtoReadFromUtils</Index>
The function <C>OKtoReadFromUtils</C> returns <C>true</C> 
only if there is an installed version of &Home; 
and if this version is greater than <B>m.n</B>. 
So, at this stage, <E>the copied code will not be read</E>, 
and the transferred functions can only be called if <Package>Home</Package> 
has been installed. 
</Item>
<Item>
(&Utils;:)
Add the test and documentation material to the appropriate files. 
The copied code can be tested by temporarily moving &Home; away from 
&GAP;'s package directory. 
</Item>
<Item>
(&Utils;:)
Release a new version of &Utils; containing all the transferred material. 
</Item>
<Item>
(&Home;:)
Edit out the declarations and implementations of all the transferred functions, 
and remove references to them in the manual and tests. 
Possibly add a note to the manual that these functions have been transferred. 
Add  &Utils; to the list of &Home;'s required packages 
in <File>PackageInfo.g</File>. 
Release a new version of &Home;. 
</Item>
<Item>
(&Utils;:) 
In due course, when the new version(s) of &Home; are well established, 
it may be safe to remove the conditional clauses mentioned in item 4 above. 
The entry for &Home; in <C>UtilsPackageLists</C> may then be removed. 
</Item>
</Enum>  

<P/> 
Finally, a note on the procedure for testing these functions. 
As long as a function being transferred still exists in the &Home; package, 
the code will not be read from &Utils;. 
So, when the tests are run, it is necessary to <C>LoadPackage("home")</C> 
before the function is called. 
The file <File>utils/tst/testall.g</File> makes sure that all the necessary 
packages are loaded before the individual tests are called. 

</Chapter>
